Victor Jacquemont Papers 1822-1833 Mss.Ms.Coll.103
American Philosophical Society
Victor Jacquemont Papers, 1822-1833
Mss.Ms.Coll.103
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
Born in Paris on August 8, 1801, the youngest of four sons of Venceslas and Rose Laisné Jacquemont, Victor Jacquemont became one of the rising stars of French natural history and an archetype for the scientist in the Romantic era. Combining youth, genius, and a rhapsodic love of nature with a life filled with masculine affection, star-crossed romance, and exotic climes, Jacquemont epitomized the romantic intellectual right up to the time of his untimely death in the Himalayas. In a career in which ill fortune and good fortune walked hand in hand, the figure of Jacquemont has all but overshadowed his substantial scientific accomplishments. The surviving correspondence of the ill-starred French botanist, Victor Jacquemont and his friend, Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874) consists of 106 letters pertaining to the development of Jacquemont's scientific career and their personal and social commitments. The correspondence was published, though not translated, in James F. Marshall, Victor Jacquemont Letters to Achille Chaper: Intimate Sketches of Life Among Stendhal's Coterie (Philadelphia: APS, 1960), APS Memoir 50.
Jacquemont, Victor, 1801-1832
Related Archival Materials note
The Papers of Charles Baron Clarke (B C555) and The Royal Botanic Garden of Calcutta (580.7 R81) contain additional information on botany in nineteenth-century India.
Jacquemont, Victor, Voyage dans l'Inde, pendant les années 1828 a 1832 (Paris: Didot Freres, 1841-1844), 4 vols. and atlas of 2 vols. (Call no.: 915.4 J16v)
Jacquemont, Correspondance de Victor Jacquemont avec sa famille et plusieurs de ses amis... (Brussels: H. Dumont, 1834)
Marshall, James F., Letters to Achille Chaper; Intimate Sketches of Life Among Stendhal's Coterie. American Philosophical Society Memoirs 50 (1960). (Call no.: B J16)
Bibliography
Jacquemont (Paris: Muséum National d'Histoire Naturelle, 1959). (Call no.: B J16b)
Gupta, Raj Jumar, "Botanical explorations of Victor Jacquemont (1801-1832)" Indian Journal of History of Science 1 (1966), 150-157. (Call no.: 509.05 In25, vol.1, no.2).
Maes, Pierre, Un Ami de Stendhal: Victor Jacquemont (Paris, Desclée de Brouwer, 1935).
Early American History Note
This manuscript collection falls outside the geographic scope of the Early American guide (British North America and the United States before 1840). It may be of interest to scholars interested in global history, international relations, imperialism, or the U.S. in the world.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Jacquemont Papers were donated by Mrs. James F. Marshall in memory of James F. Marshall in November 1986. Accession number 86-1112ms.
Scope and Contents note
The surviving correspondence of the ill-starred French botanist, Victor Jacquemont and his friend, Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874) consists of 106 letters pertaining to the development of Jacquemont's scientific career and their personal and social commitments.
Having met in Switzerland in 1822, Jacquemont and Chaper grew close in correspondence, sharing scientific ideas and gossip equally in ardent prose. The collection is far richer in documenting the first five years of friendship between the two, corresponding to the period in which Jacquemont began to transform himself from botanical dilettante into serious scientist. As such, the collection provides insight into the salon culture of 1820s Paris, and specifically the circle around Stendhal and Mérimée, as well as the vicissitudes of Jacquemont's love life, his unhappy affair with the actress Adelaide Schïasetti, and his changing ideas of love itself.
Although several lengthy letters describe Jacquemont's sojourn in the United States, Haiti, and India these episodes are, on balance, less well documented. There is, however, a fine letter describing Jacquemont's attempts to consummate a duel with General Lallemand, his revulsion at encountering chattel slavery in Brazil, and some fascinating commentary on the Himalayas -- geologically, botanically, and ethnographically.
The correspondence has been published in its entirety in James F. Marshall, Letters to Achille Chaper; Intimate Sketches of Life Among Stendhal's Coterie. American Philosophical Society Memoirs 50 (1960).
Biographical/Historical note
Born in Paris on August 8, 1801, the youngest of four sons of Venceslas and Rose Laisné Jacquemont, Victor Jacquemont became one of the rising stars of French natural history and an archetype for the scientist in the Romantic era. Combining youth, genius, and a rhapsodic love of nature with a life filled with masculine affection, star-crossed romance, and exotic climes, Jacquemont epitomized the romantic intellectual right up to the time of his untimely death in the Himalayas. In a career in which ill fortune and good fortune walked hand in hand, the figure of Jacquemont has all but overshadowed his substantial scientific accomplishments.
As a youth, Jacquemont pursued a course of classical studies at the Lycée Imperiale before entering into a scientific course at the Collège de France in 1817 to study chemistry under Louis Jacques Thenard (1777-1857). When a laboratory accident waylaid him, however, Jacquemont's interests drifted to botany. At the Château La Grange, home of the Marquis de Lafayette, Jacquemont had recovered sufficiently by 1820 to undertake a botanical tour of northeastern France, further whetting his enthusiasm for his new passion. His coterie of friends, including Adolphe Brogniart, Hippolyte Jaubert, Albert Kunth, and Adrien de Jussieu, helped sharpen Jacquemont's skills in botany, geology, and mineralogy, and together, they founded the Société d'Histoire Naturelle in Paris to promote their sciences. Jacquemont's social and intellectual ambit grew steadily, and by his twenty-first birthday, he had been received into the influential salon of étienne Delécluze in Paris, and later, into the circle gathered about Mme Pasta. He eventually counted among his valued associates such stellar figures as Stendahl and Prosper Mérimée.
Jacquemont's ascent into the stratosphere of French science was regularly accompanied by an appropriately romantic pairing of tragedy and good fortune. While taking part in a scientific excursion to the Alps in 1822, Jacquemont's friend Jaubert fell ill near the tiny village of Pinsot, requiring immediate care. The party of young scientists was taken in by a young engineer, Achille Chaper, with whom all found an immediate affinity. The bond between Jacquemont and Chaper, in particular, was instantaneous and life-long, and the two became intimate correspondents on matters social, political, personal, and scientific during the extensive periods when they were separated by science or social obligations.
Returning to his education in the fall of 1822, Jacquemont entered a course in medicine at the Faculté de Médecine in Paris, but nevertheless continued to work at the Jardin des Plantes and to take courses under Arago at the école des Mines. His relentless schedule had little impact upon his productivity: between 1820 and 1828, he contributed over 20 articles to scientific publications and never abated his naturalizing tours in and around France. Before long, however, the peculiar mix of good and ill fortune reentered the scene. Falling into a deep despair in 1826 over an "unhappy passion" for the Italian singer Adélaide Schïasetti, Jacquemont threatened to unravel. To divert him from his woes, Jacquemont's brother intervened to arrange a voyage to New York, to find solace in a new climate and in the company of an old friend, John B. Stevenson, a physician whom he had met at the Jardin des Plantes. Yet the Atlantic could not buffer against the tides of passion. While departing after a pleasant evening at the home of Pierre François Réal, Jacquemont's walking companion, the former Napoleonic officer, General Lalleman, suddenly launched into a deeply offending tirade. So insulting were the general's words, in fact, that Jacquemont immediately demanded satisfaction. Prevented by New York authorities from dueling in the States, Jacquemont vowed to avenge his wounded honor by traveling to Haiti, where civilized people could kill one another with honor (and where his brother Frédéric served as Consul). Lallemand, however, refused to follow, citing poverty among other excuses. Although the general never deigned to apologize, Jacquemont took comfort in the knowledge that the general's cowardice had been sufficiently demonstrated, and by January 1827, he felt free to leave Haiti, his honor restored.
The sojourn in Haiti, however, was not wasted. During his stay, Jacquemont engaged in some minor botanizing, but more importantly, he received an invitation from Pierre Louis Cordier of the Muséum d'Histoire Naturelle to undertake a scientific survey in India, complete with full pay and full discretion over the course of the expedition. This morsel of scientific validation was irresistible, and Jacquemont immediately returned to France via the United States to prepare. A winter in Paris served to shore up his knowledge of Asian zoology and he returned to the Jardin des Plantes to bone up on techniques for the preservation of natural specimens. After finalizing his arrangements, he departed on August 26, 1828, sailing aboard the Zélée for Pondichery.
Almost terra incognita to the French, India represented a vast scientific challenge for a country eager for information about "tropical" colonial dependencies. His travels from the Punjab to Kashmir, Bombay to Bengal, brought Jacquemont into a starling array of botanical microhabitats and geological terranes, generating reams of data and thousands of specimens that eventually fed back into French scientific circles. His pioneering geological research in the Himalayas appears to have had little influence, but his remarks on the Indian flora -- largely descriptive, but including notes on biogeography, ecology, and taxonomy -- were received eagerly. Although botanical knowledge of the tropical portions of the subcontinent were becoming increasingly well known, the information returned from the Kashmir and Himalayas as far east as Tibet was largely original. The major publication resulting from Jacquemont's three years in Indian, Voyage dans l'Inde, was widely read, and comprehended a vast scope, venturing from botany and zoology into ethnography, colonial administration, and jurisprudence. His exertions under difficult conditions and precarious health, however, took their toll. Jacquemont died of disease in Bombay on December 7, 1832.
Chaper, Pierre Achille Marie, 1795-1874; Jaubert, Hippolyte François, comte de, 1798-1874; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834; Lamarck, Jean Baptiste Pierre Antoine de Monet de, 1744-1829; Schïasetti, Adélaide; Stendhal, 1783-1842; Tracy, Antoine César Victor Charles Destutt marquis de, 1781-1864; Beyond Early America; Botany--France; Dueling.; Geology--France; Haiti--Description and travel; Himalaya Mountains--Description and travel; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859; India--Description and travel--19th century; Natural history--France; Slavery--Brazil
- Victor Jacquemont Papers, 1822-1833; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, Jacquemont, Victor, 1801-1832 (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1822 August 8; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1823 November 1; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1823 November 7; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1823 November 30; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 January 7; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 April 2; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 April 26; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 May 2; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 May; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 June 16; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 July 2; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 July 18; 4p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 September 17; 4p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 end of September; 4p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 October 8; 8p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 October 24; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 October 30; 4p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 November 1; 6p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 November 2; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1824 December 1; 12p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 January 2; 9p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 February 6; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 February 19; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 March 10; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 March 17; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 March 23; 8p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 April 3; 8p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 April 6; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 April 12; 8p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 April 20; 8p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 April 24; 8p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 May 2; 4 p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 May 6; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 May 14; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 June 5; 5p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 June 13; 5p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 June 17; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 June 20; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 June 23; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 June 25; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 June 30; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 July 1; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 July 3; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 July 4; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 July 24; 11p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 August 13; 8p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 August 23; 6p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 August 28; 6p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 September 4; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 October 19; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 October 27; 4p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 November 5; 4p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 November 26; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1825 December 1; 8p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 January 5; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 February 24; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 March 4; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 March 6; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 March 9; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 April 4; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 April 23; 3 p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 May 2; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 May 27; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 July 3; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 August 2; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 August 3; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1826 October 29; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 April 13; 12p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 May 9; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 June 7; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 June 15; 4p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 July 6; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 October 20; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 October 22; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 November 9; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 November 16; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 November 20; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 December 11; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1827 December 27; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 January 7; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 January 13; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 January 27; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 January 30; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 February 5; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 February 7; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 February 20; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 February 25; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 March 24; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 April 4; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 April 6; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 May 8; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 May 9; 1p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 May 14; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 May 18; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 May 31; 4p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 June 29; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 August 6; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 August 21; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1828 December 10; 7p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1829 August 27; 5p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1830 June 25; 4p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1831 July 21; 6p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1831 December 16; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1833 June 15; 3p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1833 August 7; 2p. (Box 1)
    - ALS to Pierre Achille Marie Chaper (1795-1874), 1833 December 9; 3p. (Box 1)